<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Vale.Rocks Portfolio</title><link>https://vale.rocks</link><description>A collection of works and creations by Declan Chidlow.</description><generator>Adduce</generator><item><title>CapChord.md</title><description><![CDATA[<head>
  <title>CapChord | Vale.Rocks</title>
  <meta property="og:title" content="CapChord"/>
  <meta property="article:section" content="Portfolio" />
</head>

<article>
<header>
	 Tech Support Business
	<h1>
		CapChord
	</h1>
</header>

<div class="readable_width">

CapChord is a mobile call-out business that I both personally own and operate. It's dedicated to helping the elderly and those with limited technical knowledge by providing support with a range of digital tasks.

## Purpose and Goal
The primary directive of CapChord is to allow those without the necessary knowledge to harness the benefits of modern technology without strife. I ensure that clients can comfortably communicate with loved ones, access essential online services, and enjoy the advantages of the information age.

## Problems and Thought Process
I've faced a few problems with CapChord. With no formal training in business I had to learn what was necessary for me to start operation. I also noticed that some clients would need not just help, but a full explanation of what I was doing and how I was doing it to assist them in understanding their own technology. This lead me to tailor my operation to explaining and teaching as well as troubleshooting and fixing in a way that is both efficient and effective.

## Lessons Learned
Through this job I've learned much. I've learnt how to liaise with clients, how to act in a professional environment, and the basics of running a business. It's also had a large hand in building my confidence as well as other soft skills.

</div>
</article>
]]></description></item><item><title>Meat_Typeface.md</title><description><![CDATA[<head>
  <title>Meat Typeface | Vale.Rocks</title>
  <meta property="og:title" content="Meat Typeface"/>
  <meta property="article:section" content="Portfolio" />
</head>

<article>
<header>
    Slightly Disturbing Typeface
	<h1>
		Meat Typeface
	</h1>
</header>

<div class="readable_width">

I'm near certain that most people, at some point, have fantasised about wielding meat as a writing tool. Well, you needn't wait any longer, as my meat typeface fulfils that dream.

The brief I received during my Certificate IV in Design was to create a typeface. As long as it had the entire alphabet, both upper and lowercase, anything went. I thought long and hard before settling on meat.

For a fleeting moment, I considered using actual meat but thought better and instead took it as a wonderful opportunity to learn about Adobe Illustrator’s 3D tools. Using some interesting texturing, I managed to concoct a fleshy, meaty typeface.

I learned a lot about letter forms during the process and ended up spending a lot of time waiting for Illustrator to compute my 3D shapes. I think it was worth it in the end, as the output was certainly *interesting*.

<img id="left" src="https://autumn.revolt.chat/attachments/d1YzFgI7Pywcz-s7KGaSHOSSCnlkTOYd_20vyQMwRN" alt="The words 'Meat Font' written in red meat. In some places the meat is missing exposing skeletal letters underneath." />

</div>
</article>
]]></description></item><item><title>Mutant_Remix.md</title><description><![CDATA[<head>
  <title>Mutant Remix Website | Vale.Rocks</title>
  <meta property="og:title" content="Mutant Remix Website"/>
  <meta property="article:section" content="Portfolio" />
</head>

<article>
<header>
	 Website
	<h1>
		Mutant Remix Website
	</h1>
</header>

<div class="readable_width">

Mutant Remix is an emoji pack built for the chat platform [Revolt](/blog/Revolt_Promotion). It combines the blobby shapes of Android's emojis of old with the crisp, bold style of Mutant Standard, creating something new and distinct.

I was tasked with building a website for the platform. A previous contributor already had a design in mind, which I fleshed out, cleaned up, and put to code. I used my static site generator, [Adduce](https://adduce.vale.rocks) and put together a site that introduces people to the project.

You can check out the live site at [mutant.revolt.chat](https://mutant.revolt.chat).

</div>
</article>
]]></description></item><item><title>Photography.md</title><description><![CDATA[<head>
  <title>Photography | Vale.Rocks</title>
  <meta property="og:title" content="Photography"/>
  <meta property="article:section" content="Portfolio" />
</head>

<article>
<header>
	 Pictures
	<h1>
		Photography
	</h1>
</header>

<div class="readable_width">

I'm by no means a professional photographer, but these are a series of photos I’ve taken. I don’t have a professional camera, so I use my Nokia G22’s inbuilt camera and then touch them up, where necessary, in Adobe Lightroom. I enjoy taking pictures of the natural world when the opportunity presents itself, although I’m far from opposed to taking pictures of other subjects.

I upload most of what I take to Unsplash for anyone to use, free of charge. My account is [@OuterVale](https://unsplash.com/@outervale).

<img id="left" src="https://images.unsplash.com/photo-1698750297812-c27bd0d48ab5" alt="A tree with vibrant pink-red leaves stands against a clear blue sky, in front of a one-story house with a brick façade. The sunlight filters through the leaves, highlighting their color." />

<img id="right" src="https://images.unsplash.com/photo-1691918917939-eebdc97244e3" alt="Close-up view of a vibrant green moss-covered surface with a small, delicate mushroom with a tan cap standing out against the textured background. The sunlight accentuates the intricate details of the moss and the slender stem of the mushroom." />

<img id="right" src="https://images.unsplash.com/photo-1696060159045-69025bb6ddfb" alt="A panoramic view of a picturesque lakeside town nestled at the foot of rugged, snow-capped mountains. The vibrant blue lake is prominent, with boats visible on the water, and the settlement spreads out into the green and brown patchwork landscape leading to the towering peaks under a clear blue sky." />

<img id="right" src="https://images.unsplash.com/photo-1691918917740-45c1f0d8183d" alt="A single mushroom with a textured brown cap and slim stem stands prominently in the center of a vibrant green moss-covered forest floor. The background is a softly blurred view of a forest with tall trees, suggesting a quiet, serene woodland scene." />

</div>
</article>
]]></description></item><item><title>Pam_Carters_Scriptural_Poetry.md</title><description><![CDATA[<head>
  <title>Pam Carter's Scriptural Poetry | Vale.Rocks</title>
  <meta property="og:title" content="Poems By Pam"/>
  <meta property="article:section" content="Portfolio" />
</head>

<article>
<header>
	 Poem Compilation
	<h1>
		Pam Carter's Scriptural Poetry
	</h1>
</header>

<div class="readable_width">

For many years, my grandmother has been writing poems. Upon seeing my work, she requested that I compile them into a proper, professionally printed book.

Using InDesign, I sifted through over 20 years of word documents, photographs, and treasured fragments to create something that would do her poems justice. The layout and styling also incorporate a personal touch, as it was created for someone whom I love very much.

Beyond creating something that honoured my grandmother's dedication to poetry, it also proved an excellent opportunity to broaden my knowledge of designing for press and physical mediums, and I gained a lot of knowledge doing it.

<img id="left" src="https://autumn.revolt.chat/attachments/lSH-X8OWpTKjR2QXZM7Y35B0w5o32GjQmACOkTlJPs" alt="A hardcover book with a painting-style cover titled 'Spiritual Poems by Pamela' on a pale pink background. The subtitle 'Volume One - He Is There' is at the top, and the author's name 'Pamela Maitland Carter' is at the bottom. The cover image depicts a pastoral landscape with a figure in a red hat amidst greenery and flowers under a blue sky." />

<img id="right" src="https://autumn.revolt.chat/attachments/jSP2GLY4xKnxMK_7qOT0P_Ev4hw00RqmDZvp53W3Fw" alt="An open book is resting on a beige surface with the left page titled 'THE POWER OF PRAYER' in bold letters and featuring a text passage. The right page contains a photograph of a silhouetted person with arms outstretched against a backdrop of a forest and a golden sunset. The book is halfway open." />

</div>
</article>
]]></description></item></channel></rss>