<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Vale.Rocks Portfolio</title><link>https://vale.rocks</link><description>A collection of works and creations by Declan Chidlow.</description><generator>Adduce</generator><item><title>devoposters.md</title><description><![CDATA[<head>
  <title>Devo Posters</title>
  <meta property="og:title" content="Devo Posters"/>
</head>

<header>
	 Graphic Design Project
	<h1>
		Devo Posters
	</h1>
</header>

Devo is a band I've been a fan of ever since I was very young. Dancing along to "Whip It!" on my MP3 player, hearing their scores for films and games, and seeing Mark Mothersbaugh on Yo Gabba Gabba are all etched into my brain.

When I was tasked with making a set of posters for a band of my choosing while studying for my Cert IV in Graphic Design, it was a no brainer to choose them. Their distinct style and captivating visuals offered the perfect canvas to showcase my skills and pay homage to a band that has been a significant inspiration.

The brief was to create three posters, each taking inspiration from the colours and styles of a specific decade. I chose to represent the 1920s, 1960s, and 2000s. I researched each era and built up a palette for my posters.

For my 1920s poster, I selected the era's more muted, warmer colours, tapping into the sepia toned elegance of the past. My geometric, stylized silhouettes attempted to echo the modernist approach of the time.

In contrast, my 1960s poster leaned into more psychedelic, vivid colours, capturing the free-spirited essence of the era. The palette and overall design take much inspiration from Arnold Skolnick's 1969 Woodstock poster.

My 2000s design was perhaps the most open in terms of palette. Being the era where digital technologies really took hold, there was a full digital palette at my disposal. I chose the bright, sometimes garish, colour palettes of the Frutiger Metro aesthetic.

With each poster, I made an earnest attempt to not only capture the colours but also celebrate the artistic evolution and technological advancements that defined each period.

<img id="left" src="https://autumn.revolt.chat/attachments/D5eqFQeMKnvnhpi-GmyH6H6IZIn0n4IabNNWKZYHZ-" alt="A series of colorful posters for the band DEVO, also referred to as The De-Evolution Band, displayed on an exterior brick wall. The repeated posters feature stylized images of the band members with bold graphics and slogans like 'Are we not men we are DEVO!' and 'The Truth About DE-EVOLUTION'. A blurred cyclist passes by in the foreground, capturing a sense of motion on the street." />
]]></description></item><item><title>CapChord.md</title><description><![CDATA[<head>
  <title>CapChord</title>
  <meta property="og:title" content="CapChord"/>
</head>

<header>
	 Tech Support Business
	<h1>
		CapChord
	</h1>
</header>

CapChord is a mobile call-out business that I both personally own and operate. It's dedicated to helping the elderly and those with limited technical knowledge by providing support with a range of digital tasks.

## Purpose and Goal
The primary directive of CapChord is to allow those without the necessary knowledge to harness the benefits of modern technology without strife. I ensure that clients can comfortably communicate with loved ones, access essential online services, and enjoy the advantages of the information age.

## Problems and Thought Process
I've faced a few problems with CapChord. With no formal training in business I had to learn what was necessary for me to start operation. I also noticed that some clients would need not just help, but a full explanation of what I was doing and how I was doing it to assist them in understanding their own technology. This lead me to tailor my operation to explaining and teaching as well as troubleshooting and fixing in a way that is both efficient and effective.

## Lessons Learned
Through this job I've learned much. I've learnt how to liaise with clients, how to act in a professional environment, and the basics of running a business. It's also had a large hand in building my confidence as well as other soft skills.
]]></description></item><item><title>meattypeface.md</title><description><![CDATA[<head>
  <title>Meat Typeface</title>
  <meta property="og:title" content="Meat Typeface"/>
</head>

<header>
    Slightly Disturbing Typeface
	<h1>
		Meat Typeface
	</h1>
</header>

I'm near certain that most people, at some point, have fantasised about wielding meat as a writing tool. Well, you needn't wait any longer, as my meat typeface fulfils that dream.

The brief I received during my Certificate IV in Design was to create a typeface. As long as it had the entire alphabet, both upper and lowercase, anything went. I thought long and hard before settling on meat.

For a fleeting moment, I considered using actual meat but thought better and instead took it as a wonderful opportunity to learn about Adobe Illustrator’s 3D tools. Using some interesting texturing, I managed to concoct a fleshy, meaty typeface.

I learned a lot about letter forms during the process and ended up spending a lot of time waiting for Illustrator to compute my 3D shapes. I think it was worth it in the end, as the output was certainly *interesting*.

<img id="left" src="https://autumn.revolt.chat/attachments/d1YzFgI7Pywcz-s7KGaSHOSSCnlkTOYd_20vyQMwRN" alt="The words 'Meat Font' written in red meat. In some places the meat is missing exposing skeletal letters underneath." />
]]></description></item><item><title>futurefrequencies.md</title><description><![CDATA[<head>
  <title>Future Frequencies</title>
  <meta property="og:title" content="Future Frequencies"/>
</head>

<header>
	 Graphic Design Project
	<h1>
        Future Frequencies
    </h1>
</header>

The brief I received for this student project was to create album artwork for a fictitious band of my creation. I came up with Neon Delta, an embodiment of indie synthwave vibes.

I've always felt that synthwave has a very futuristic yet 80s feel to it. It's as if it presents the analogue future that never materialised. I've always found that, within this genre, there is a slight dystopian undertone. I set out to encapsulate that in my album art.

There were a few ways to go about representing it that I attempted. I took a picture of my music visualizer, which promptly corrupted, leaving me with what I thought was a really striking effect. I also tried to represent sound waves by layering undulating blocks, but neither of these quite achieved what I had envisioned.

<img id="left" src="https://autumn.revolt.chat/attachments/dpSiyk0Iwug4xM7vGh1eTP3O28eW1XqAUZ1wZ4EBYL" alt="Album art featuring an abstract design with neon-like horizontal lines in blue and green that create an audio waveform pattern. The text 'FUTURE FREQUENCIES NEON DELTA' is overlaid in a distorted typeface." />

<img id="left" src="https://autumn.revolt.chat/attachments/jyfiUvM4l3yvRRKhoFf_U3yhrSpFkHWOdJqgMBGjp-" alt="Album art for 'Future Frequencies' featuring a minimalist design with layered wavy blocks. The blocks are in an assortment of colors against a dark background. The album's title is written in white block letters." />

Ultimately, I found success in imitating a wood grain hi-fi system with a large oscilloscope embedded, featuring the album name. I tied in the dystopian elements I had been aiming for by transforming it into a slightly militaristic apparatus, adorned with an array of purposeful buttons. This captured exactly the style I was striving for, and with a bit of refinement, became my final product.

<img id="left" src="https://autumn.revolt.chat/attachments/JAVxAsSuokeK7SP1jVh7Jh35dAeZY2Ly6wIqTvm35t" alt="Album art showcasing a vinyl record with the title 'FUTURE FREQUENCIES' by 'NEON DELTA'. The left side of the image depicts a stylized vintage control panel with a green oscilloscope screen and knobs, and buttons that include a red 'NUKE' button. Below it reads 'Exercise complete caution when operating device.' The right side features the actual vinyl record with grooves and the album's title printed near the center. The background has a wooden texture, blending the old-fashioned control equipment aesthetic with the timeless vinyl record." />
]]></description></item><item><title>photography.md</title><description><![CDATA[<head>
  <title>Photography</title>
  <meta property="og:title" content="Photography"/>
</head>

<header>
	 Pictures
	<h1>
		Photography
	</h1>
</header>

I'm by no means a professional photographer, but these are a series of photos I’ve taken. I don’t have a professional camera, so I use my Nokia G22’s inbuilt camera and then touch them up, where necessary, in Adobe Lightroom. I enjoy taking pictures of the natural world when the opportunity presents itself, although I’m far from opposed to taking pictures of other subjects.

I upload most of what I take to Unsplash for anyone to use, free of charge. My account is [@OuterVale](https://unsplash.com/@outervale).

<img id="left" src="https://images.unsplash.com/photo-1698750297812-c27bd0d48ab5" alt="A tree with vibrant pink-red leaves stands against a clear blue sky, in front of a one-story house with a brick façade. The sunlight filters through the leaves, highlighting their color." />

<img id="right" src="https://images.unsplash.com/photo-1691918917939-eebdc97244e3" alt="Close-up view of a vibrant green moss-covered surface with a small, delicate mushroom with a tan cap standing out against the textured background. The sunlight accentuates the intricate details of the moss and the slender stem of the mushroom." />

<img id="right" src="https://images.unsplash.com/photo-1696060159045-69025bb6ddfb" alt="A panoramic view of a picturesque lakeside town nestled at the foot of rugged, snow-capped mountains. The vibrant blue lake is prominent, with boats visible on the water, and the settlement spreads out into the green and brown patchwork landscape leading to the towering peaks under a clear blue sky." />

<img id="right" src="https://images.unsplash.com/photo-1691918917740-45c1f0d8183d" alt="A single mushroom with a textured brown cap and slim stem stands prominently in the center of a vibrant green moss-covered forest floor. The background is a softly blurred view of a forest with tall trees, suggesting a quiet, serene woodland scene." />
]]></description></item><item><title>poemsbypam.md</title><description><![CDATA[<head>
  <title>Poems By Pam</title>
  <meta property="og:title" content="Poems By Pam"/>
</head>

<header>
	 Poem Compilation
	<h1>
		Poems By Pam
	</h1>
</header>

For many years, my grandmother has been writing poems. Upon seeing my work, she requested that I compile them into a proper, professionally printed book.

Using InDesign, I sifted through over 20 years of word documents, photographs, and treasured fragments to create something that would do her poems justice. The layout and styling also incorporate a personal touch, as it was created for someone whom I love very much.

Beyond creating something that honoured my grandmother's dedication to poetry, it also proved an excellent opportunity to broaden my knowledge of designing for press and physical mediums, and I gained a lot of knowledge doing it.

<img id="left" src="https://autumn.revolt.chat/attachments/lSH-X8OWpTKjR2QXZM7Y35B0w5o32GjQmACOkTlJPs" alt="A hardcover book with a painting-style cover titled 'Spiritual Poems by Pamela' on a pale pink background. The subtitle 'Volume One - He Is There' is at the top, and the author's name 'Pamela Maitland Carter' is at the bottom. The cover image depicts a pastoral landscape with a figure in a red hat amidst greenery and flowers under a blue sky." />

<img id="right" src="https://autumn.revolt.chat/attachments/jSP2GLY4xKnxMK_7qOT0P_Ev4hw00RqmDZvp53W3Fw" alt="An open book is resting on a beige surface with the left page titled 'THE POWER OF PRAYER' in bold letters and featuring a text passage. The right page contains a photograph of a silhouetted person with arms outstretched against a backdrop of a forest and a golden sunset. The book is halfway open." />
]]></description></item><item><title>Mutant_Remix.md</title><description><![CDATA[<head>
  <title>Mutant Remix Website</title>
  <meta property="og:title" content="Mutant Remix Website"/>
</head>

<header>
	 Website
	<h1>
		Mutant Remix Website
	</h1>
</header>

Mutant Remix is an emoji pack built for the chat platform [Revolt](/blog/Revolt_Promotion). It combines the blobby shapes of Android's emojis of old with the crisp, bold style of Mutant Standard, creating something new and distinct.

I was tasked with building a website for the platform. A previous contributor already had a design in mind, which I fleshed out, cleaned up, and put to code. I used my static site generator, [Adduce](https://adduce.vale.rocks) and put together a site that introduces people to the project.

You can check out the live site at [mutant.revolt.chat](https://mutant.revolt.chat).
]]></description></item><item><title>koko.md</title><description><![CDATA[<head>
  <title>Koko Chocolate Crafters</title>
  <meta property="og:title" content="Koko Chocolate Crafters"/>
</head>

<header>
	 Branding Project
	<h1>
		Koko Chocolate Crafters
	</h1>
</header>

I, like many others, am quite a fan of chocolate. That's why I was very happy when I got the brief while completing my Certificate IV in Design to create a branding system and some packaging for a fictional Margret River business by the name of Koko Chocolate Crafters.

The target audience for the business was primarily female chocolate lovers over the age of 30, so I tailored my packaging while designing it. The challenge lay in creating a visual identity that exuded both luxury and approachability.

I designed the brand to appear premium and entice users in a way that spoke directly to the refined tastes of the mature audience while ensuring an inclusive appeal.

Once I had the brand system established, I got to work on the packaging. I created three designs, one for each of the three launch flavours, and I'm very happy with the end result. It blends premium appeal with the lure of a delicious taste.

<img id="left" src="https://autumn.revolt.chat/attachments/XQ8gvFYxWZ7lBeX1Fb12YeEAiavbpTeZ9VIJsMLhfD" alt="Three colorful KOKO chocolate bars with distinctive packaging. From left to right: the first bar has a purple and green geometric design symbolizing mint, the middle bar showcases a brown coconut on blue background for coconut flavor, and the third bar features an orange fruit on a green leafy background, representing orange flavor." />
]]></description></item><item><title>smashburger.md</title><description><![CDATA[<head>
  <title>Smash Burger</title>
  <meta property="og:title" content="Smash Burger"/>
</head>

<header>
	 Branding Project
	<h1>
		Smash Burger
	</h1>
</header>

I must say, I'm quite the fan of a good burger, so when I got the brief while completing my Certificate IV in Graphic Design to brand a fictional foodtruck by the name of Smash Burger, I wanted to do it justice.

The brief specified that they were targeting 16 to 25 year olds looking for great burgers and that they needed to stand out among the crowd at events.

Naturally, I designed their logo with big, bold typography that stands out from the background. I followed that up with an impactful red and yellow colour palette to be adorned on every surface. This really helped it stand out and cement its own identity.

With the brand defined, I moved on to designing a range of touchpoints, such as the packaging and the design of the truck itself. I think the final product really cemented a strong identity and fulfilled the brief to its fullest extent.

<img id="left" src="https://autumn.revolt.chat/attachments/PlyBLo0AyE8ppOBZ2vMisJpA-QGj4YgIs-4j8SF8Hj" alt="A black and red food truck with the slogan 'Bangin' Burgers' parked in front of a building with glass facade. The truck has an open side window for service, displaying a visible menu, and has a sign that reads 'SMASH! Burger' A leafless tree stands next to the truck." />
]]></description></item></channel></rss>